window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Digital_Logic - Number_System — Slot 7 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Number_System — Slot 7",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Sign extension is a step in <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>floating point multiplication</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>signed 16 bit integer addition</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>arithmetic left shift</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>converting a signed integer from one size to another.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>converting a signed integer from one size to another.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/821/gate2002-1-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The 2's complement represent representation of the decimal value -15 is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1111</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>11111</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>111111</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10001</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>10001</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/819/gate2002-1-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The decimal value of 0.25 <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>is equivalent to the binary value 0.1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is equivalent to the binary value 0.01</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is equivalent to the binary value 0.00111.....</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>cannot be represented precisely in binary.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>is equivalent to the binary value 0.01</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/818/gate2002-1-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Consider the values of \\(A = 2.0 \\times 10^{30}, B = -2.0 \\times 10^{30}, C = 1.0\\), and the sequence <br><pre><code> X:= A + B          Y:= A + C   \n X:= X + C          Y:= Y + B</code></pre> <br>\nexecuted on a computer where floating point numbers are represented with 32 bits. The values for X and Y will be <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>X = 1.0, Y = 1.0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>X = 1.0, Y = 0.0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>X = 0.0, Y = 1.0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>X = 0.0, Y = 0.0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>X = 1.0, Y = 0.0</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/661/gate2000-2-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The number 43 in 2's complement representation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(01010101\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>11010101</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(00101011\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10101011</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(00101011\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/629/gate2000-1-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Zero has two representations in: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Sign-magnitude</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2's  complement</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1's  complement</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Sign-magnitude</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1495/gate1999-2-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Booth's coding in 8 bits for the decimal number -57 is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0-100+1000</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0-100+100-1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0-1+100-10+1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>00-10+100-1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>0-100+100-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1473/gate1999-1-20\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the domain set of an attribute consists of signed four digit numbers. What is the percentage of reduction in storage space of this attribute if it is stored as an integer rather than in character form? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>80%</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>20%</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>60%</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>40%</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>60%</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1693/gate1998-2-20\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The octal representation of an integer is \\((342)_8\\). If this were to be treated as an eight-bit integer in an 8085 based computer, its decimal equivalent is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>226</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-98</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>76</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-30</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>-30</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1654/gate1998-1-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Given \\(\\sqrt{(224)_r} =(13)_r\\).<br>\nThe value of the radix r is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2255/gate1997-5-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following floating-point number representation. <br>\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \\begin{array}{cc}31\\;\\;\\hspace{15pt}&amp;\\hspace{15pt}24\\end{array} &amp; \\begin{array}{cc}23\\hspace{15pt}&amp;\\hspace{15pt}0\\end{array} \\\\\\hline \\text{Exponent}&amp;\\text{Mantissa}\\\\ \\hline \\end{array}\\) <br>\nThe exponent is in 2's complement representation and the mantissa is in the sign-magnitude representation. The range of the magnitude of the normalized numbers in this representation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0 to 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.5 to 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{-23}\\) to 0.5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0.5 \\text{to }\\left(1-2^{-23}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0.5 \\text{to }\\left(1-2^{-23}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2729/gate1996-1-25\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Booth's algorithm for integer multiplication gives worst performance when the multiplier pattern is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>101010 ... 1010</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>100000 ... 0001</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>111111 ... 1111</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>011111 ... 1110</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>101010 ... 1010</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2727/gate1996-1-23\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The number of 1's in the binary representation of (3*4096+15*256+5*16+3) are: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>9</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2624/gate1995-2-12-isro2015-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The 2's complement representation of \\((-539)_{10}\\) is hexadecimal is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>ABE</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>DBC</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>DE5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9E7</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>DE5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/728/gate2001-2-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The exponent of a floating-point number is represented in excess-N code so that: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The dynamic range is large.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The precision is high.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The smallest number is represented by all zeros.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Overflow is avoided.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The smallest number is represented by all zeros.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80201/gate1987-1-vii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
